# GRAHAM A. ROSS

613-769-1331

· graham.a.ross@gmail.com ·

\_\_\_\_\_

Software Architect/Developer with over 20 years of experience in public and private sectors specializing in complex enterprise wide applications architecture and development. Expertise in Microsoft .NET, architecture, design, integration and development of software systems involving various components and subsystems using the latest technologies and design patterns.

## CONSULTING EXPERIENCE

#### **DEC 2014-JULY 2015, SEPT 2016-FEB 2019**

## **SOFTWARE ARCHITECT, IMMIGRATION, REFUGEES AND CITIZENSHIP CANADA (IRCC)**

Application Software Architect Level 3 for Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC). A member of the Integration Services team, developed workflow services to integrate with the Siebel CRM system. Development and maintenance of the middle tier services for applications such as Passport, ETA, Case Status and Express Entry.

#### **OCT 2013-NOV 2014**

### .NET DEVELOPER, ELECTIONS CANADA

Principle .Net developer for the creation of the unit and integration tests including the continuous integration framework. Produced the technical and deployment documentation. Liaised with the business analyst and project director to ensure the application meets all business requirements.

#### **JULY 2011-SEPT 2013**

## .NET DEVELOPER, SOFTWARE ARCHITECT, CORRECTIONAL SERVICES OF CANADA (CSC)

Developed a 3 tier web based application within a continuous integration framework. Produced the technical and deployment documentation. Developed the deployment and configuration packages for use with a fault tolerant Radware system. Assisted the performance lab to ensure the application met the performance and security requirements. Provided knowledge transfer to the CSC technical and operational staff.

#### **JAN 2009-JULY 2011**

#### SENIOR APPLICATIONS DEVELOPER, APPLICATION ARCHITECT CASEWARE IDEA

Assessed stakeholder requirements and policies, evaluated potential solutions and alternative technologies, and provided recommendations to provide business solutions. Analyzed functional requirements to identify and develop procedures, decision flows and design patterns. Developed the data dictionary and analyzed the business, systems, architecture and database by assessing the current departmental methods and procedures and documenting the database content, structure and the sub-

systems. Analyzed and documented the interfaces of the system including automating manual process within the sub-system and with new and existing external systems.

#### **SEPT 2007-JAN 2009**

#### **SOFTWARE ARCHITECT, WORLD REACH SOFTWARE**

Designed and documented system components and database content, structure and application subsystems while analyzing the current methods and procedures. Defined and documented the interfaces and integrated and leveraged the functionality from application sub-systems to external systems to create the overall solution. Defined input and output sources, which included preparing a detailed plan for the technical design phases. Integrated approved technologies into the overall solution architecture.

### JULY 2006-SEPT 2007, FEB 2005-JULY 2006

## **SENIOR DEVELOPER, CASEWARE IDEA**

Created and built a prototype to test the performance impact of COM interop. Evaluated and selected 3rd party .NET components. Ported existing VB6 and C++ code to C# .NET. Designed, developed and tested the new .NET components. Participated in the design of detailed program specifications for program components and objects. Analyzed data sources to define the input and output sources, including a detailed plan for the technical design phase and obtained approval from all stakeholders involved. Developed templates and documented system specific standards for programming, documentation and testing which included program libraries, data dictionaries and naming conventions.

## **EDUCATION**

## **ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING TECHNOLOGY, ALGONQUIN COLLEGE**

Obtained diploma after 3 years of studying Electronic Engineering Technology.

## **SKILLS**

- Application developer (Government, Financial analysis, Call Center)
- Enterprise developer (Multi-tier, fault tolerant, distributed systems)
- Expert in Microsoft .NET, C#, Web Services, Windows Communication Foundation (WCF)
- Windows Workflow Foundation (WWF)
- UI development using Microsoft ASP.Net, Javascript, MVC, Windows Forms
- Development environment: Visual Studio, TFS, GIT
- Linux, Docker container, Azure IOT Edge, MQTT
- Android mobile development: Java, Android Studio, Modbus/TCP

## **ACTIVITIES**

An active member and leader of lectures in the Ottawa .NET user group.